Welcome back to Colab and welcome back to our business project.
콜랍에 다시 오신 걸 환영합니다 사업 프로젝트에 다시 오신 것도요
So again our assignment, we are due to create meeting minutes based on an audio file.
다시 숙제가 나왔네요 오디오 파일을 기반으로 회의록을 만들어야 해요
Uh so I found this very useful data set.
아주 유용한 데이터 세트를 찾았어요
It's typical hugging face to have a perfect data set for us.
완벽한 데이터를 얻기 위해 포옹하는 얼굴이죠
Um, it's a data set called meeting Bank, which is apparently a pretty well known, uh, data set,
미팅 뱅크라는 데이터 세트인데 꽤 유명한 데이터 세트예요
a benchmark created from the City council's six major US cities.
미국 시의회의 6대 주요 도시에서 만든 척도죠
Um, so I use this.
그래서 이걸 써요
I downloaded a particular Denver City Council meeting, and I actually just took a ten minute segment
덴버시 의회 회의 중 하나를 다운로드해서 10분 정도 편집한
of it, uh, to be used for our experiment here.
부분을 실험에 사용했어요
Uh, either ten or maybe it was a 20 minute segment of it.
10분인가 20분 정도 됐을 거예요
Um, but anyway, took that audio cut and I saved it on my Google Drive because my idea here is I'd
어쨌든 오디오를 잘라 구글 드라이브에 저장했어요 구글 드라이브에 있는 건 뭐든 취할 수 있는
like this product to be able to take anything that is in one's Google Drive, or if you're building
제품이 되길 원했거든요 회사의 드라이브에 있는 회사를
this for a company in the company's drive and be able to use that to generate meeting minutes.
위해 이걸 구축하고 있다면 회의록 생성하는 데 사용할 수 있어요
So as part of this project, a little sidebar is we're also going to see how you can get a colab to
이 프로젝트의 일부로 작은 부록을 드리죠 구글 드라이브에서 Colab이 읽게
read from your Google Drive.
하는 방법을 보여드릴게요
So we begin, as usual with some imports these sorry with Pip installs, the one little extra here is.
늘 그렇듯 수입부터 시작할게요 Pip 설치부터요 하나 더 있어요
You'll notice that we're also going to install OpenAI on this colab as well.
이 Colab에도 OpenAI를 설치할 거예요
We're not just using hugging face, we're using a bunch of hugging face, uh, packages.
포옹하는 얼굴만 쓰는 게 아니라 포옹하는 얼굴과 소포를 잔뜩 사용해요
And also OpenAI library.
오픈AI 라이브러리도 있어요
We do some imports and including an OpenAI import as well as everything else.
오픈AI와 다른 모든 것들을 수입하는 일도 해요
Um, and then we're going to set some constants.
그리고 몇 가지 상수를 설정할 거예요
We're going to use an audio model called whisper, one that may be used yourself.
위스퍼라는 오디오 모델을 사용할 거예요 여러분이 사용할 수도 있는 거죠
When I'd set you this assignment, uh, previously.
전에 과제를 드렸을 때요
Um, and then this is the llama 3.18 billion instruct model that we'll be using as well.
이건 라마 3이고요 180억 개짜리 지시 모델도 사용하게 될 거예요
So here this is the new capability that that that you'll be learning.
여기 여러분이 배우게 될 새 기능이 있어요
Today as well a little extra.
오늘도 좀 더 주세요
This is how you connect Colab to your Google Drive.
콜랍을 구글 드라이브에 연결하는 방법이죠
Super simple.
아주 간단해요
And it's just a drive dot mount.
드라이브 닷 마운트예요
And you tell it where locally you would like to.
원하는 곳을 말해주면 돼요
Mount the drive.
구동축을 올려요
That's basically it.
그게 다예요
And then I've set a constant for myself of within my drive.
제 열정에 대한 고정관념을 세웠어요
Uh, it's uh, in the I've got a folder called LMS and within that I have Denver Extract dot mp3, which
LMS라는 폴더에 들어 있는데 그 안에 덴버의 닷 mp3 추출물이 있어요
is the MP3 recording of, uh, this, uh, segment that somewhere between 10 and 20 minutes from the
MP3 녹음 파일인데 덴버 시의회에서 10분에서 20분 정도 분량으로
Denver City Council.
녹음한 거예요
So if I run this, it pops up with a, um, a it's connected to Google the first.
이걸 실행하면 뭐가 떠요 구글 1번과 연결됐죠
I'm running this for the second time, and the first time I ran this, it of course popped up with an
이걸 두 번째로 실행하고 있어요 처음 실행했을 때 인증과 함께
authentication, uh, selection for me to confirm that I'm signed in with my Google account and I grant
나타났죠 구글 계정으로 로그인되어 엑세스 권한을 부여받았다는 걸 확인하기 위한 선택이요
This time it's telling me it's already mounted there.
이번에는 이미 설치됐다고 하네요
Um, if I were to go to the folder here, would be able to go through my Google drive and see all my
이 폴더로 가면 구글 드라이브로 가서/콘텐츠/드라이브
all my files under slash content slash drive.
아래에 있는 모든 파일을 볼 수 있어요
So we then sign in to the Huggingface hub.
그런 다음 H깅페이스 허브에 로그인하죠
Here we go.
시작할게요
Login successful.
로그인 성공이에요
And we also sign in to OpenAI.
오픈AI에도 로그인해야 해요
So this is very similar.
이것도 비슷해요
We get our OpenAI key which is also I've set the OpenAI key uh in the secrets of this colab.
오픈아이 키를 준비했어요 오픈아이 키도 콜랍에 넣어 뒀죠
Um, and so we retrieve that key and then we call the usual OpenAI uh, constructor to, to establish
그 키를 회수하고 일반적인 OpenAI 생성자를 호출해 인터페이스
the, the interface connection.
연결을 설정해요
But this time I am passing in that OpenAI, OpenAI API key.
이번엔 OpenAI API 키를 넘길게요
Uh, you remember in the past I've not had to specify this because I've relied on the fact that the
기억하시겠지만 과거에는 이걸 명시할 필요가 없었죠 환경 변수가 설정되어 있다는 사실에
environment variable is set.
의존했으니까요
This time I'm passing it in explicitly.
이번엔 명시적으로 전달하죠
So there we go.
자, 됐어요
That is now established the OpenAI connection.
오픈아이와의 연결 고리가 만들어졌죠
And then what am I going to do?
그럼 전 어떻게 하죠?
I'm going to take this audio file, which is sitting on my Google Drive that's now mapped to this colab.
이 오디오 파일을 취하겠습니다 구글 드라이브에 있는 거죠 이제 이 Colab에 매핑됐어요
And then I'm going to call OpenAI dot audio.
OpenAI. audio를 호출할 거예요
Dot transcriptions dot create, which is very similar to other OpenAI API methods we've used.
.Rrcript는 .Create입니다 다른 오픈AI API 방식과 아주 유사하죠
It's particularly similar to the one when we actually made, made it to speak, made it generate audio.
실제로 말을 하도록 만들었을 때 오디오를 생성하게 했던 것과 특히 유사하죠
I passed in the name of the model, the whisper one model, the file, and that I want the response
모델 이름을 입력했어요 위스퍼 원 모델, 파일 응답을 텍스트로 원한다는
in text.
거죠
And then I will print what comes back from OpenAI's whisper model.
오픈아이 위스퍼 모델에서 나온 것을 프린트할 거예요
So it's been provided with a bunch of audio, or it's being provided as we speak with a bunch of audio
많은 오디오가 제공되었죠 프론티어 모델이라 부르는
that is now calling the frontier model, and we are currently waiting to get back a transcription of
많은 오디오가 제공되고 있어요 현재 그 회의의 녹취본을 받으려고 기다리고
that meeting.
있죠
Well, that's happening.
그렇게 됐네요
I'm going to keep going so that we can get ahead on on the other things.
Get it, get it, get it, get it, get it, it, it, it, it. 다른 걸 할 수 있게 계속할게요
I have to run.
난 가야 해요
We're then going to set up the prompt for llama three, and there's going to be a system prompt, a
다음엔 llama3 프롬프트를 설정하겠습니다 시스템 프롬프트 시스템 메시지,
system message and a user prompt system messages.
사용자 프롬프트가 있어요
You're an assistant that produces meetings of minutes from transcripts with a summary, key discussion
비서가 회의록을 작성하고 요약, 핵심 토론 포인트
points, takeaways and action items with owners in markdown, uh, and then a user prompt that says
테이크아웃, 행동 항목을 작성해요 소유주가 마크다운된 사항이죠
below is the transcript of a an extract transcript.
아래에 추출한 회의록의 프롬프트가 있어요
That's fine.
괜찮아요
I thought my English was bad, but it's okay.
제 영어 실력이 별로인 줄 알았는데 괜찮았어요
Other Denver Council meeting.
다른 덴버 의회 회의요
Please write minutes in markdown, including a summary with attendees, location and date, discussion
참석자와 장소, 날짜, 토론 포인트 포장 음식점, 소유주와 함께하는 활동 아이템 등을
points, takeaways, and action items with owners.
포함해 요약본으로 작성하세요
And then I shove in the transcript of the meeting right after that user prompt.
그런 다음 회의 녹취록을 넣어요 사용자 프롬프트 바로 다음에요
Here is the transcript.
여기 녹취록이에요
It just got printed out And it's a long old transcript.
방금 인쇄했는데 아주 긴 필사본이에요
The Denver City Council meeting.
덴버 시의회 회의요
Talked for quite a while, and a lot of it was about Indigenous Peoples Day, which was the upcoming
한동안 대화를 나눴는데 대부분 토착민의 날에 관한 거였어요 곧 다가올 연방
federal holiday.
공휴일이죠
And there was some debate about the right way for the council to recognize Indigenous Peoples Day.
의회가 토착민의 날을 어떻게 인정할지 논쟁이 벌어졌어요
If you read through all of this text or if you listen to the, the, the audio.
이 글을 전부 읽거나 오디오를 들어 보세요
So this is all now in text in this transcription variable.
이건 모두 텍스트로 되어 있고 이 전사 변수에 들어 있어요
So we started with audio.
그래서 오디오로 시작했죠
We now have text thanks to OpenAI's whisper one model.
오픈라이의 위스퍼 원 모델 덕분에 텍스트가 생겼죠
We now create our system and user prompt.
이제 시스템과 사용자 프롬프트를 생성하죠
Now this will look familiar to you.
이제 눈에 익을 거예요
This is our quant config.
이건 우리의 퀀트 구성이에요
We're going to be quantizing again.
다시 수량화할 거예요
Why not.
안 될 거 없죠
It was very effective with lambda 3.1 before it reduced the memory significantly down to 55. five gigabytes.
람다 3에 아주 효과적이었어요 메모리가 55로 크게 줄어들기 전까지는요 5기가바이트요
But it did not.
하지만 아니었죠
At least His performance seemed to be perfectly good to us.
적어도 우리가 보기엔 연기가 완벽했어요
Maybe you tried it without quantizing to see how much better the joke was.
얼마나 웃긴지 보려고 수량화하지 않고 해 봤을 수도 있죠
Um.
네
I wouldn't be surprised if it didn't make much difference at all.
별 차이가 없다고 해도 놀랍지 않을 거예요
Quantization is very effective.
퀀타이즈는 아주 효과적이에요
Okay, it's time for action.
이제 행동할 시간이에요
This should all be quite familiar to you because this is what we did last time.
지난번에 했던 거니까 익숙할 거예요
We are going to create a tokenizer for Lama using the auto tokenizer Frompretrained method.
라마를 위한 토큰마이저를 만들 거예요 교육된 오토 토큰마이저를 사용해서요
We're going to do this business of setting the pad token as before.
이전처럼 패드 토큰을 설정하는 작업을 할 거예요
Then we're going to call the apply chat template function method.
채팅 템플릿 함수 적용 메서드를 호출할게요
Passing in the messages the this this right here.
메시지를 전달하는 거죠
We're passing that in.
전달하는 거죠
And this of course includes the whole transcript.
물론 녹취록도 포함해서요
It includes the text of the whole meeting and the user prompt.
전체 회의의 텍스트와 사용자 프롬프트를 포함하죠
And we're going to put that massive amount of text on our GPU.
GPU 상에 엄청난 양의 텍스트를 Put 할 거예요
We're going to stream again.
다시 방송할 거예요
So use this text stream object.
이 텍스트 스트림 객체를 사용하세요
And then here we go.
이제 시작이에요
This is.
맞아요
This is when we create our model.
이제 모델을 만들 거예요
We create the auto model for causal Elm.
인과율 엘름 오토모델을 제작해요
We pass in the llama model name.
라마 모델명을 통과시키죠
We say, please use a GPU if we've got one, which we do.
GPU가 있으면 사용하라고 하고 실제로 사용하죠
We're using the T4 box, the small GPU box for this.
T4 박스를 사용하고 있어요 작은 GPU 박스요
And we pass in our quantization config.
퀀타이즈 구성에서 넘기죠
I'm going to start this running now because it will take take a while.
시간이 좀 걸리니까 실행을 시작할게요
I should have started running before I was talking.
말하기 전에 뛰어야 했어요
That would have been smarter.
그게 더 현명했을 거예요
Uh uh.
네
And so we're going to then create the model and then we're going to do the action.
그런 다음 모델을 생성하고 액션을 실행하죠
Action is to call generate on model.
동작은 생성기를 호출하는 거죠
And when you call generate you have to pass in the inputs, which of course is now this entire tokenized,
생성기를 호출할 때는 입력값을 넘겨야 합니다 입력값은 전체 토큰화 된 프롬프트와
uh prompts and transcript.
녹취록이죠
This is a bit bigger than you're used to before.
비트가 좀 더 커졌어요
We used to say in the maximum new tokens was 80.
새 패는 최대 80장이라고 했죠
Now we're saying maximum new tokens is 2000 because there could be quite a hefty response.
최대 토큰은 2000이라고 했어요 응답이 많을 수 있으니까요
Um, so, uh, uh, we that should be enough space to get back our meeting minutes.
그러니까, 어, 어 이 정도면 회의록 돌려받기에 충분한 공간이겠죠? Get it
And then we're also providing the streamer, which is telling it that it can stream results back into
그리고 스트리머도 제공하는데 Cab으로 결과를 보낼 수 있다고
our colab.
알려줘요
While it's going to be thinking for a little bit, I'll tell you what's going to happen next is going
잠시 생각할 동안 다음에 일어날 일을 말씀드리죠 회의 내용을 여기서
to stream the meeting minutes back in here.
스트림으로 비트로 보낼 거예요
Um, afterwards, what we can also do is we can also just get that text by taking the outputs, taking
그 후에 할 수 있는 또 다른 일은 출력을 가져와서 텍스트를 get 하는 것입니다 출력자의 첫
the first of the outputs, and there only will be one.
번째 것을 가져와서 하나만 남게 되는 거죠
And then decoding that using tokenizer dot decode.
토큰라이저 닷디코드로 그걸 해독해요
Uh, and that's something we will then put into a variable called response.
응답이라는 변수에 넣을 거예요 put it
Well here come the minutes.
결과가 나왔네요
Um.
네
It's about to come.
곧 나와요
It's so far.
너무 멀어요
Just put the, the uh.
Put it을 눌러요
The transcript in their.
녹취록 말이에요
Minutes of the Denver City Council meeting Monday, October the 9th and location attendees who are the
덴버시 의회 회의록 10월 9일 월요일 장소 참석자들과 누가 참석했는지를요
Summary.
요약해 보죠
They met on Monday, October the 9th to discuss and adopt a proclamation for Indigenous Peoples Day.
10월 9일 월요일에 만나서 원주민의 날을 위한 선언문을 논의하고 채택했어요
Councilman Lopez presented the proclamation.
로페즈 의원이 선언문을 발표했죠
Key discussion points.
핵심 논점이에요
Takeaways.
포장 음식점요
It was adopted recognizing the importance of the day.
시대의 중요성을 깨닫고 채택된 거죠
They emphasized the importance of inclusivity and respecting all cultures.
포용과 모든 문화를 존중하는 걸 강조했죠
Some actions with owners and actions.
어떤 행동들은 소유주와 행동을 동반하죠
Councilman Lopez and clerk.
로페즈 의원과 서기요
Clerk is to attest and affix the seal of the City and Council of Denver to the proclamation.
서기는 시와 덴버 의회의 인장을 보증하고 서명하세요
And then, uh, Councilman Lopez to transmit a copy of the proclamation to the Denver American Indian
로페즈 시의원이 성명서 사본을 덴버 아메리카 인디언 위원회와
Commission and some other areas, and then some next steps at the end.
다른 곳에 전달하고 최종적으로 다음 단계를 밟았죠
So I've got to hand it to llama 3.1.
라마 3의 활약을 인정해야겠네요 1번요
This seems to be a very comprehensive, very clear, very thorough set of minutes with attendees with
아주 포괄적이고 명확하며 아주 철저한 회의록인 것 같아요
date with with, uh, all of the right format and the right sections.
모든 형식과 섹션을 제대로 갖춘 참석자들이 참석한 회의록이죠
Now, you'll notice, of course, that it's come in markdown format.
보다시피 마크다운 포맷으로 나왔어요
And you're familiar from, uh, when we were working with frontier models before in Jupyter Notebook
전에 프론티어 모델을 작업했을 때 주피터 노트북을 사용했었는데
locally, that we can use this display markdown response as our way to see that in markdown in the Colab.
이 표시형 마크다운 반응을 이용해서 Colab에서 마크다운을 확인할 수 있어요
And here we have, uh, the minutes of the Denver City Council meeting, um, and, uh, organized into
여기 덴버시 의회 회의록이 있습니다 요약과 요점,
those various sections of the summary, the takeaways, the action items, and the next steps.
행동 항목 다음 단계로 나뉘어 있죠
So I give you an application that uses a frontier model and an open source model to take audio and convert
그래서 저는 오디오를 녹취록으로 변환하기 위해 프런티어 모델과 오픈 소스 모델을 사용하는 응용 프로그램을
it to a transcript, and convert that transcript to a meeting summary with actions and next steps.
제공합니다 그 녹취록을 액션과 다음 단계가 있는 회의 요약으로 변환하죠
Well, the obvious exercise for you.
당신에겐 당연한 운동이죠
I hope you've already guessed what it's going to be.
뭘 준비했는지 이미 짐작하셨길 바라요
It's easy peasy to now put that into a nice user interface.
사용자 인터페이스로 쉽게 옮길 수 있어요.
You can use Gradio very similar to what we've had in the previous week, and you can bring up this into
지난주에 다룬 것과 아주 유사하게 그래디오를 사용할 수 있어요 작고 멋진 그래디오 인터페이스로
a nice little Gradio interface.
이걸 불러올 수 있죠
Perhaps you could type out the name of a file on your Google Drive and press Generate Minutes.
구글 드라이브에 파일 이름을 입력하고 통화 기록 생성 버튼을 누르세요
It will read in that audio, convert it to text, and then convert it to meeting minutes actions, takeaways,
오디오에서 읽고 텍스트로 변환하고 회의록 동작, 테이크아웃, 다음 단계로
next steps.
변환해요
So that's the task for you.
그게 당신 작업이에요
Please go away and do that.
가서 그렇게 해요
And I can't wait to see some terrific user interfaces.
훌륭한 사용자 인터페이스를 빨리 보고 싶어요
Please do push the code when you've got it.
코드가 나오면 누르세요
I would love to see them and I will see you for the next lecture in a moment.
보고 싶네요 잠시 후 다음 강의에서 뵙죠